(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.1",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
湊あくあ 卒業ライブ 「あくあ色に染まれ！」
Minato Aqua Graduation LIVE: Aqua Iro ni Somare!
ここは 1人の女の子が
This is a place where a girl...
夢を追いかけた場所。
...chased her dreams.
ここは 1人の女の子が
This is a place where a girl...
夢を掴んだ場所。
...made her dreams come true.
私 湊あくあは...
I, Minato Aqua...
2024年
As of 2024,
8月 28日をもって
August 28th...
ホロライブを
From Hololive...
卒業します。
I am graduating.
皆さんどうも、こんあくあー！
Hello everyone, Kon-Aqua!
あくたんのこと、好きすぎ！？
Do you love Akutan too much!?
皆様のおかげで、
Thanks to everyone,
無事５周年を迎えることができました！
I was able to safely reach my 5th anniversary!
３、２、１、６周年おめでとう！
3, 2, 1, Happy 6th anniversary!
湊あくあ ～卒業～
Minato Aqua ~Graduation~
等身大のインタビュー
Life-size Interview
本日はインタビューよろしくお願いします。
Thank you for the interview today.
よろしくお願いします。
Thank you for having me.
ではまず、お名前を教えてください。
First, please tell me your name.
はい。えっと、湊あくあです。
Yes. Um, I'm Minato Aqua.
湊ってどういう漢字書かれるんですか？
How do you write the kanji for "Minato"?
え、あの、さんずいに奏でるで、湊です。
Uh, well, it's the water radical and "play," it's Minato.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
では、ご職業は何をされていますか？
Now, what is your profession?
ご職業...
Profession...
アイドルです。
I'm an idol.
あ、アイドルなんですね。なんか見た目は、すごくメイドさんな感じなんですけども。
Ah, so you're an idol. Your appearance is very much like a maid, though.
アイドルです！
I'm an idol!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
では続いて、好きな食べ物は何ですか？
Moving on, what is your favorite food?
好きな食べ物は、ずっとオムライスだったんですけど...
My favorite food has always been omelet rice, but...
最近変わりまして。
It's changed recently.
あ、変わられたんですね。
Oh, it changed?
卵です！
Eggs!
元々の素材が、好きになったと。
So you started to like the raw ingredient.
素材が好きでした。
I liked the ingredient.
最近気づきました。
I realized it recently.
あ、そうなんですね。そしたらオムライスだけではなく、目玉焼きとかも好きということですか？
I see. So, you like not only omelet rice but also fried eggs and such?
はい！好きです。
Yes! I like them.
あ、ちなみに目玉焼きには、何をかける派でしょうか？
By the way, what do you usually put on your fried eggs?
塩胡椒かな...
Salt and pepper, I guess...
あ、同じですね。ありがとうございます。
Ah, same here. Thank you.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
続きまして、ズバリ湊あくあさんのチャームポイントは？
Next, what is Minato Aqua's charm point?
後頭部です。
The back of my head.
あ、後頭部。あ、綺麗な後頭部ですね、こちら。
Ah, the back of your head. It's a beautiful back of the head, this one.
はい、これ以上は言えません。
Yes, I can't say more than that.
あ、何か触れてはいけないんでしょうかね。
Oh, is it something I shouldn't touch upon?
はい。ちょっと色々あって。
Yes. There are reasons.
あ、そうなんですね。
I see.
すみません。
I'm sorry.
好きな色を教えてください。
Please tell me your favorite color.
好きな色は、あくあ色です。
My favorite color is Aqua color.
あくあ色、いいですね。
Aqua color, that's nice.
あくあ色の、どういうところがやっぱり良いなと思いますか？
What part of Aqua color do you think is good?
あくあ色は、やっぱ自分の色なので、ピンクと水色であくあ色、良いです。
Aqua color is my color, so pink and light blue make Aqua color, it's good.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
では続きまして、ホロライブプロダクションに所属して、
Moving on, since joining Hololive Production,
湊あくあさん自身が成長したなって思うところはありますか？
is there anything about yourself that you feel has grown?
成長...。でもやっぱり、人と円滑にコミュニケーションが取れるようになりました。
Growth... But after all, I've become able to communicate smoothly with people.
これまでの活動してきた中で、一番の思い出は何ですか？
What is your best memory from your activities so far?
色々あるんですけど、やっぱり一番と言ったらソロライブと全体ライブです。
There are many things, but if I had to pick the best, it would be the solo lives and group lives.
ソロライブをすることは、デビューした当時からの目標で。
Doing a solo live was a goal since I debuted.
ステージに立った時はすごく緊張したけど、みんなの応援のおかげで頑張れました。
I was very nervous when I stood on stage, but I was able to do my best thanks to everyone's support.
みんなが照らしてくれた、
I can never forget the sight of the
あくあ色のサイリウムの景色は今でも忘れられません。
Aqua-colored glow sticks lighting up for me.
それでは続きまして、今一番腹を割ってお話ししたい人はいますか？
Moving on, is there someone you want to talk to from the heart right now?
ああ...
Ah...
YAGOO社長。
President YAGOO.
お久しぶりです。
Long time no see.
覚えてますか？
Do you remember me?
もちろんです。
Of course.
本当ですか？
Really?
あ... あの、緊張されてますか？
Uh... Um, are you nervous?
いや、大丈夫です。
No, I'm okay.
私はめちゃくちゃ緊張しています。
I'm extremely nervous.
あの、今日はお時間をいただき、ありがとうございます。
Um, thank you for your time today.
こちらこそありがとうございます。
Thank you as well.
ずっとたくさん聞きたいことがいっぱいあるので、今日は...
There are so many things I've wanted to ask, so today...
お話ししていければと思います。
I hope we can talk.
はい。いっぱい喋ってくださいね。
Yes. Please talk a lot.
ちょっと... 苦手なんで喋るの。
Uh... I'm not good at talking.
お願いします！
Please do!
お願いします。
Please.
じゃあ、1回目からいきます。
Let's start with the first one.
はい。
Yes.
まず、えっと、簡単なものから。
First, starting with something easy.
責任感で、社長としての責任感で
Out of responsibility, as a CEO...
胃が痛くなったりとか、うわーってなったりすることはありますか？
Do you ever get stomach aches or feel overwhelmed?
あんまり...
Not really...
あんまりない？
Not really?
あんまり緊張するタイプではないかなという風に思いますかね。
I don't think I'm the type to get nervous easily.
そうなんですか？
Is that so?
本当ですか？
Really?
はい。ただまあ...
Yes. But...
基本日々こういろいろ課題を抱えているので、
Essentially, I face various challenges every day, so...
「これを今日やらなきゃ」っていう感じで、朝早く起きちゃうことはありますね。
I sometimes wake up early thinking, "I have to do this today."
じゃあちょっと、ホロライブについて聞こうと思います。
Then, I'd like to ask something about Hololive.
はい。
Yes.
まずは、どうしてホロライブを作ろうと思ったんですか？
First, why did you decide to create Hololive?
っていう。
...I'd like to ask.
そうですね。なんというか...
Well, how should I put it...
元々その初音ミクさんみたいな、ああいうキャラクターで、
Originally, with characters like Hatsune Miku...
海外の人も含めて楽しませるような、そういうコンテンツっていいなと思っていました。
I thought it'd be great to have content that entertains fans worldwide.
うんうん。
Uh-huh.
でも、初音ミクさんって初音ミクさん以外の人たちがいるわけではないので、
But, since there aren't many others besides Hatsune Miku...
たくさんの人が人気になれるわけではないなと思っている中で...
I felt that it didn't allow many people to become popular.
何かVTuber的なシステムっていうのを自分たちで開発して、
So, by developing a VTuber-like system ourselves...
そういう色々な配信者さんだったりとか、クリエイターの方が、
Various streamers and creators...
初音ミクさんのようなバーチャルタレントとして活動できると、すごく...
Could perform as virtual talents like Hatsune Miku...
世界中のファンの方を喜ばせられるかもしれないなと思って。
And that might please fans around the world.
ホロライブのシステムを開発して、こういうサービスを始めようと思いました。
So I developed the system and started this service.
ああ。
I see.
まさかこんな大所帯になるとは思ってなかったって感じなんですかね。最初は。
Did you not expect it to become such a large group at first?
最初はそうですね。こんな大所帯になるとは...
Initially, yes. I didn't expect it to become this large...
ある程度やっぱり海外の方に、すごくたくさんのファンの方に届けていきたいと思っていたので、
I wanted to reach a lot of fans, including those overseas...
もちろん規模として大きいものを目指していましたけれど、
So I was aiming for something on a large scale...
予想よりも順調に成長しているのかなとは思います。
But I think it has grown more smoothly than I expected.
おお〜。なんか...
Oh~. It's like...
ちゃんと社長ですね？
You're actually a CEO!
これ失礼なのかな？
Is that rude of me to say?
ちゃんと社長ですね！すごい！
You're really a CEO! Amazing!
じゃあ続いて、ここまでホロライブのお話を聞かせていただいたんですけれど、
Next, we've talked about Hololive so far...
次は私、湊あくあについて聞いていこうと思います。
...but next, I'd like to ask about me, Minato Aqua.
ここが一番大事です。
This is the most important part.
よろしくお願いします。
Thank you.
それではいきます。
Here we go.
私、湊あくあは、
Have I, Minato Aqua...
ホロライブプロダクションに貢献できていましたか？
...contributed to Hololive Production?
ズバリ！教えてください！
Give it to me straight! Tell me!
貢献できていたと思いますね。まあ、
I believe you have contributed. Well...
ホロライブプロダクションというよりは、やっぱり湊あくあさんっていうタレントさんが、
Rather than the production, a talent like Minato Aqua...
TikTokとかでも流行るような楽曲みたいなものを提供というか、
Provides music that trends on TikTok and so on...
そういった活動を実現することができて。
You were able to achieve those activities.
いろんな若い人にとっての、憧れの存在とかなれたんじゃないかなと思っています。
I think you've become an inspiration for many young people.
そう思いますか？
Do you think so?
はい。そう思いますか。
Yes, do you think so.
おお...。
Oh...
どんな印象を持たれているんですか？湊あくあに対して。
What kind of impression do you have of Minato Aqua?
基本的にはすごく芯の強い方だなって...
Essentially, I think you're a person with a very strong core...
本当ですか？
Really?
思っています。
I think.
活動としてはやっぱり、アイドル的な側面もあると思うんですけど。
In terms of activities, you have an idol-like side...
やっぱり配信の、ゲームがうまいというところがやっぱり最もこう、
...but your exceptional gaming skills are probably the most...
ギャップというか、ギャップって言うとあれですけどね。
...striking "gap," if I can call it that.
になる部分なのかなという風に思っていました。
...it's that kind of part, I think.
おお〜。
Oh~.
それでは最後に、ここまで私からの質問ばかりだったんですけれど。
And finally, I've been the one asking all the questions so far.
社長から私へ、伝えたいことなどあったりしますでしょうか？
Is there anything you would like to tell me, CEO?
やっぱり6年という長い期間活動していただいて、本当にありがとうございました。
Thank you so much for your activities over these long 6 years.
本当にお疲れ様でしたと言いたいです。
I want to say, thank you for your hard work.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
僕としてもまだまだ心残りな部分もあるんですけれど、
I still have some lingering regrets, but...
本当にこの6年、ご一緒できたことがすごく良かったと思っております。
I'm really glad we were able to work together for these 6 years.
ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
本当にホロライブに入れていただいて、ありがとうございました。
Truly, thank you for letting me join Hololive.
ということで、なんかちょっとエモい感じになりましたけれども、
So, it's become quite emotional, but...
こんな感じで、
With that...
対談は以上ということで。
...this concludes our talk.
ご対談は以上ということで。
That concludes our talk.
ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
お疲れ様でした。
Good job today.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
社長と話してみていかがでしたか？
How was it talking with the CEO?
めっちゃ緊張しました。
I was so nervous.
なんか、生きてるんだなぁって、
It made me realize that...
実感しました。
...he's actually alive.
そうですね、生きてらっしゃいますね。
Right, he is indeed alive.
これまでの活動できて、社長とお話することってなかったですか？あくあさん。
In your activities so far, have you ever talked with the CEO, Aqua-san?
やっぱりそうですね、社長だし。
Well, he is the CEO, after all.
YAGOOは妖精みたいな存在だから。
YAGOO is like a fairy-like existence to me.
一生会えない、天然記念物なのかなぐらいに思ってました。
I thought he was like a natural monument I'd never meet in my life.
あ、そうなんですね。
Ah, I see.
ちゃんといました。
He really existed.
ちゃんと存在してましたか、よかったです。
He truly existed? That's good to hear.
では続いての質問です。
Now for the next question.
今、一番感謝を伝えたい人はいますか？
Is there someone you'd like to express your gratitude to most right now?
いっぱいますけど...
There are many people, but...
一番はマネージャーさんです。
...the one I'm most grateful to is my manager.
お、マネージャーさん。
Oh, your manager.
手紙を書いてきたので、読みます。
I've written a letter, so I'll read it now.
ありがとうございます。では、手紙よろしくお願いします。
Thank you. Please go ahead with the letter.
マネージャーさんへ
To my manager,
マネージャーさん！お元気ですか！
Manager! How are you doing?
マネージャーさんのことは配信でもちょくちょく話が出てくる
Your name often comes up in my streams...
ユニコーンのアイコンだった有能マネージャーさんです。
...as the "Capable Manager" with the unicorn icon.
2020年頃から約4年間お世話になりました。
You've taken care of me for about four years since 2020.
ホロライブでは担当マネージャーさんが変わることがよくある中で、
In Hololive, managers often change, but...
ここまで変わることなく来れたこと、ものすごく奇跡だと思ってます。
...the fact that you've stayed with me all this time is a total miracle.
担当した当時の私は、まだめっちゃガキで尖ってて、
When you first took charge of me, I was such a brat and very prickly.
マネージャーさんに何度もご迷惑をおかけしたと思います。
I'm sure I caused you a lot of trouble back then.
今でも、私が配信ばかりして返事返すの遅かったり、
Even now, I get so focused on streaming that I'm slow to reply...
時々通じない日本語を使ってしまったりしてご迷惑をおかけしました。
...and I've troubled you by using Japanese that sometimes makes no sense.
それでも、ここまで見捨てず担当して下さりありがとうございました。
Even so, thank you for not giving up on me and continuing to be my manager.
いつも現場へ行くとジュースとお菓子を用意してくださっていたり、
You always had juice and snacks ready for me at recordings...
旅行のお土産をくれました。
...and you'd give me souvenirs from your travels.
外の仕事が苦手でいつもご飯を食べてこなくても、
I'm not good at outside work and often wouldn't eat anything...
仕事が頑張れたのはマネージャーさんのおかげです。
...but I could push through thanks to you.
私が人間関係や社会との向き合い方で悩んでいた時も、
When I was struggling with relationships or how to deal with society...
たくさんアドバイスや勇気づけてくださる言葉をくれました。
...you gave me so much advice and words of encouragement.
田舎から上京して何も分からなくて、
When I first came to Tokyo from the countryside, knowing nothing...
親元を離れ頼る人もいなかった時も、
...and had no one to rely on after leaving my parents...
第三の母として支えて下さいました。
...you supported me like a third mother.
第一の母はくみこ、
My first mother is Kumiko,
第二の母はマリン、
my second mother is Marine,
第三の母はマネージャーさんです。
and my third mother is you, Manager.
この4年間、たくさん愛情を込めて湊あくあをサポートして下さり、
Thank you so much for supporting Minato Aqua with so much love...
本当にありがとうございました。
...over these past four years.
私の担当でいてくれて本当によかったです！
I'm so glad you were my manager!
湊あくあより
From Minato Aqua.
素敵なお手紙ありがとうございました。マネージャーさん感動してましたね。
Thank you for the lovely letter. Your manager was very moved.
本当に感動してるのかな？
Are they really moved?
あくあさん自身も、さっき、なんか涙目な感じがしてましたけど。
You looked like you were getting a bit teary-eyed yourself just now.
私が泣くわ、これ！やだ、泣いて...
I'm the one who's going to cry! Oh no, I'm crying...
やっぱり、あくあさんにとって第三のお母さんですね。
Truly, she is a third mother to you.
第二の母マリンで引っ込んだんだけど、涙。
My tears retracted at "second mother Marine," though.
そうですね、ちょっと第二の母マリンで、ちょっとクスって私なっちゃったんですけど。
Yeah, I also chuckled a bit at the "second mother Marine" part.
いや、本当に感謝してます。
But really, I'm truly grateful.
それでは、最後の質問です。
Well then, for the final question.
はい。
Yes.
あくあさんご自身において、変わらないものはなんですか？
What is something about yourself, Aqua-san, that has never changed?
変わらないもの...
Something that hasn't changed...
はい。
Yes.
お。
Oh?
44.5kg
ここは、一人の女の子が夢を追いかけた場所
This is the place where a girl chased her dream.
ここは、一人の女の子が夢を掴んだ場所
This is the place where a girl grasped her dream.
そしてここは、一人の女の子が新たな道を歩み出す場所
And this is the place where a girl takes her first steps on a new path.
湊あくあさんにとってホロライブとは？
What is Hololive to Minato Aqua?
居場所
A place where I belong.
好きだった　この場所
I loved this place.
やめられない漫画を途中で閉じて
Closing the manga I couldn't put down,
顔を上げて　気づくように
Looking up to realize it.
居心地いい日向もいつの間にか
Even the cozy sunny spot, before I knew it,
影になってた　黄昏（たそがれ）る
had turned into a shadow at dusk.
君と会って
Meeting you...
過ぎる時間忘れるくらい夢中で話した
we talked so much, forgetting the time.
僕の夢は
My dream is...
ここではない　どこかへ
to go somewhere that isn't here.
帰り道は　帰り道は
The way home, the way home...
遠回りをしたくなるよ
makes me want to take a detour.
どこ行けば　どこに着くか?
Where will I end up if I go there?
過去の道なら　迷うことがないから
On the paths of the past, I never get lost.
弱虫
A coward,
新しい世界へ
towards a new world.
今　行きたい　行きたい
I want to go now, I want to go.
強くなりたい
I want to become strong.
好きだった　この場所
I loved this place.
一歩目　踏み出そう
Let's take the first step.
街明かりが寂しくと感じるのは
The city lights feel lonely
見慣れた景色と違うから
because the view is different from what I know.
いつもの交差点が見えなくなって
The usual intersection is out of sight,
どこにいるかわからない
and I don't know where I am.
人は誰も　変わることになれていなくて
No one is used to things changing,
昨日と同じように
just like yesterday,
今日も
today
明日も
and tomorrow,
ここにいたくなるんだ
they want to stay here.
知らない道
An unknown path...
あと何回　歩けるだろう
I wonder how many more times I can walk it.
夢の方へ
Towards dreams,
愛の方へ
towards love.
風は道を選んだりはしないよ
The wind doesn't choose its path.
このまま　このまま
Just as it is, just as it is,
ワンウェイの標識
a one-way sign.
でも　行くんだ　行くんだ
But I'm going, I'm going,
戻れなくても
even if I can't return.
君と離れるのは　悲しいけど
It's sad to be apart from you,
大事な別れだ
but it's an important parting.
もともと広い世界
The world was wide to begin with,
知らなきゃいけない
and I have to see it.
いつかきっと
Someday, for sure,
違う道を選んだ
we'll know we chose different paths
輝く未来のためと　互いにわかるだろう
for the sake of a bright future.
風のように
Like the wind,
like the wind,
思いのままに生きてみよう
let's try to live as we please.
過去がどんな　眩しくても
No matter how bright the past may be,
未来はもっと眩しいかもしれない
the future might be even brighter.
帰り道は　帰り道は
The way home, the way home...
遠回りをしたくなるよ
makes me want to take a detour.
どこ行けば　どこに着くか?
Where will I end up if I go there?
過去の道なら　迷うことがないから
On the paths of the past, I never get lost.
弱虫
A coward,
新しい世界へ
towards a new world.
今　行きたい　行きたい
I want to go now, I want to go.
強くなりたい
I want to become strong.
好きだった　この場所
I loved this place.
大切な思い出
Precious memories
過ぎてきたこの場所
The place we've passed through
ロケットサイダー
Rocket Cider
拝啓、人類は
Dear humanity,
快晴なんか無くして
we've lost the clear blue skies
大抵が最低です。
Most of it is terrible.
廃材置き場の毎日で
Everyday in this scrap yard.
「衛星都市にいこう」
"Let's go to the satellite city,"
あなたは言った
you said.
「1.5リットルの
"A 1.5-liter
現実逃避行さ」
reality escapade."
乱反射　世界が透けて
Diffused reflection, the world turns transparent
サイレンが遠くで鳴った
A siren echoed in the distance
もう対流圏界面
We're already at the tropopause
週末、ぼくらは
On the weekend, we're
月の裏側で
on the far side of the moon
「なんにもないね」なんて
"There's nothing here," we'll say,
くだらなくて笑いあうだろう
laughing at how silly it is
それからぼくらは恋におちて
And then, we fell in love
この旅の果てなんて
Even if we knew
わかっていたって知らないふりさ
the end of this journey, we'd pretend not to
今なら
If it's now
八月の雪が降ったあの日は
On that day in August when it snowed
ビードロを
It looked like we were
覗いたように見えた
peering through a glass bead
「ねえ涙がなんか止まんないんだ
"Hey, for some reason, the tears
昨日から」
haven't stopped since yesterday"
わずかに、
I saw,
崩壊する都市が見えた
the city crumbling slightly
それは最後の夏でした
That was the final summer
週末、ぼくらは
On the weekend, we're
月の裏側で
on the far side of the moon
傷つけあうのなんて
Hurting each other is just foolish,
馬鹿らしくて笑いあうだろう
so we'll laugh it off
それからぼくらは恋におちて
And then, we fell in love
ふたり気付いていたって
Even if we both noticed,
もうね、この夢はさめないよ
you know, we won't wake up from this dream
そうさぼくら
That's right, we're
世界の片隅で
in a corner of the world
「失くしてばっか」なんて
"I keep losing things," we say,
心なんて埋まらなくても
even if our hearts can't be filled
何度もぼくらは星を巡るよ！
We'll travel around the stars again and again!
拾った銀貨使って
Let's use the silver coin we found
ジュース買って分けあって飲もう
to buy juice and share it
「サイダーがいいな」
"I'd like some cider"
ラブポーション
Love Potion
不思議な顔をすると
When you make a puzzled face,
なぜかキミが愛おしくなる
for some reason, you become so dear to me
その素振り、仕草に
At those movements and gestures,
恋しちゃったみたいなんだ
it seems I've fallen in love
これからまた、
From now on,
遠く離れている
once again,
星に行ってしまう
you're going to a star far, far away
なんて、イヤだけど
Something like that... I hate it, but
これだけは言わせてね
please let me say just this
「また会えるさ！」
"We'll meet again!"
「離れたくない…」
"I don't want to leave..."
いつだってそばにいるよ
I'll always be by your side
だってもっと一緒にいたいの
Because I want to be with you more
ずっとずっと見てるからね
Because I'll be watching you forever and ever
ふたりで描こう人生日記
Let's write our life's diary together
新しい星にも
Even on a new star
新しい星に
To the new star
慣れたつもりでいたけど
I thought I had gotten used to it
なにか物足りない
Something is missing
君の笑い声だった
It was the sound of your laughter
あれからどれくらい
How much time has passed since then?
カレンダーをめくったのかな
I wonder how many calendar pages I've turned
ひとりでは
When I'm alone
帰り道
On the way home
寄り道もしないから
Since I don't take any detours
怒られない
No one scolds me
涙が出るの
And tears come out
いっつだってそばにいるよ
I'm always by your side
だってもっと一緒にいたいの
Because I want to be together more
ずっとそっと見てるからね
I'll always be watching you softly
ふたりで描こう 人生日記
Let's draw our life diary together
ラブラブピポー ピッピハリピポー
Love Love People, Pippi Happy People
ああああ
Ahhhh
いっつだってそばにいるよ
I'm always by your side
だってもっと一緒にいたいの
Because I want to be together more
ずっとそっと見てるからね
I'll always be watching you softly
ふたりで描こう 人生日記
Let's draw our life diary together
そうこのまま 時を越えて
Yes, just like this, beyond time
誰の声も届かない場所へ
To a place where no one's voice can reach
ふたりだけの場所へ
To a place just for the two of us
ココロをつなぐ 人生日記
A life diary that connects our hearts
ふたりで描こう 人生日記
Let's draw our life diary together
ひとりが辛いから 二つの手をつないだ
Because being alone is hard, we joined two hands
ふたりじゃ寂しいから 輪になって手をつないだ
Because just two of us is lonely, we joined hands in a circle
きっとそれが幾千の力にもなり
Surely that will become a strength of thousands
どんな夢も断てる気がするんだ
I feel like I can cut through any dream
高く飛べ 高く空へ
Fly high, to the high sky
高く蹴れ 高く声を上げ
Kick high, raise your voice high
いつか挫けた その日の向こうまで
To the other side of that day when I once gave up
きみの声 忘れない 涙も忘れない
I won't forget your voice, I won't forget the tears
これから始まる
It's starting from here
希望という名の未来を
A future named hope
その足は歩き出す
Those feet start walking
やがて来る過酷も
Even the hardships that will eventually come
みんなで作った輪は 大きくなりすぎて
The circle we made together has grown too large
時にはきみがどこにいるのかも わからなくなって
Sometimes I lose track of where you are
そっと誰かがくれた 優しい言葉が
The kind words someone gently gave me
きみの物語 教えてくれたんだ
Told me your story
腕をかき 風を切れ
Pump your arms, cut through the wind
前を向き 涙が滲むほどに
Look forward, until tears well up
真っ直ぐ この空を駆け抜けろ
Run straight through this sky
きみもひとり 僕もひとり
You're alone, I'm alone
みんなが孤独でいるんだ
Everyone is lonely
この輪の中で
Inside this circle
この輪の中で 気づかないうちに
Within this wheel, before I even noticed it
その足は震え出す
Those legs began to tremble
小さな過酷にも
Even at small hardships
僕ら皆同じ夢を見てた
We were all dreaming the same dream
過ぎ去る１ページの...
A single page that passes by...
ここからは一冊しか持って行けないよ
From here on, I can only take one book with me
それでよかったのかい？
Was that all right?
胸には強さを
Strength in my heart
気高き強さを
A noble strength
頬には涙を
Tears on my cheeks
一滴の涙を
A single drop of tear
高く飛べ 高く冴え 高ければ 高く声を上げ
Fly high, be sharp and high, if it's high, raise your voice high
いつか挫けた その日の向こうまで
Until beyond that day when I once faltered
君の声 忘れない
I won't forget your voice
涙も 忘れない
I won't forget the tears
これから始まる 希望という名の未来を
The future called hope that is about to begin
その足は歩き出す
Those legs begin to walk
やがて来る過酷も
Even the hardships that will eventually come
乗り越えてくれるよ
You'll overcome them
信じさせてくれるよ
You make me believe so
昨日も今日も晴天で 入道雲を見ていた
Yesterday and today were clear skies, and I was watching the cumulonimbus clouds
怠いくらいの快晴だ 漫ろに目を閉じて
The weather's so clear it's almost sluggish, listlessly I close my eyes
それはどうも簡単に 思い出せやしないようで
It seems it's not quite so easy to remember
年を取った現状に 浸ってたんだよ
I was soaking in my current state of having aged
大人ぶった作戦で 不思議な合図立てて
With an adult-like strategy, setting a mysterious signal
「行こうか、今日も戦争だ」 立ち向かって手を取った
“Let's go, it's war today too,” we stood up and took each other's hands
理不尽なんて当然で 独りぼっち強いられて
Unreasonableness was a matter of course, and being forced into loneliness
迷った僕ら 憂鬱になりそうになってさ
Lost as we were, we were about to become depressed
背高草を分けて 滲む太陽睨んで
Pushing aside the tall grass, glaring at the blurring sun
君はさ、こう言ったんだ 「孤独だったら、おいでよ」
And you, you said this: “If you're lonely, come here”
騒がしさがノックして 生まれた感情さえも
The noisiness knocked, and even the feelings that were born
頭に浮かんでは萎んだ 幻なのかな
Flickered in my head and then withered, were they just illusions?
秘密基地に集まって 「楽しかったね」って単純な
Gathering in the secret base, just simply saying “That was fun”
あの頃を思い出して 話をしよう
Remembering those days, let's talk
飛行機雲飛んでって 「眩しいね」って泣いていた
The contrails flying away, we were crying saying “It's so bright”
君はどんな顔だっけ 何故だろう、思い出せないな
What kind of face did you have? I wonder why, I can't remember
「忘れないでさぁ、進もう」
"Don't forget it, let's move forward."
もどかしさに何度でも
No matter how many times I feel frustrated,
明日を夢に見てた
I was dreaming of tomorrow.
戻らない 先のある世界へ
To a world that won't go back, a world with a future,
「僕たちで変えよう」
"Let's change it ourselves."
「思い出して、終わったって」
"Remember, even if it's over,"
「秘密基地も、冒険も」
"the secret base, the adventure,"
あの日に迷い込んだ
the story that we strayed into
話の事も
on that day.
独りぼっちが集まった
Loners gathered together,
子供たちの作戦が
the children's plan
また今日も廻り出した
started turning again today.
「また、何処かで。」
"Somewhere again."
「涼しいね」って言い合った
We said to each other, "It's cool, isn't it?"
夏空は透明だ
The summer sky is transparent.
泣かない様に、吸い込んで
Inhale so you don't cry,
「さようなら」しよう
and let's say "goodbye."
秘密基地に集まって
Gathering at the secret base
笑い合った夏の日に
on that summer day when we laughed together,
また何処かで思い出して
remembering it again somewhere,
出会えるかなって
wondering if we can meet again.
何度でも描こう
Let's draw it over and over again.
明日の明日もきっと 一人じゃ辿り着けない
Even the day after tomorrow, I probably can't reach it alone.
涙の数の想いだけ 伝えたい
I just want to convey as many feelings as the number of tears.
あの日始まった 絆結ぶ 戸惑いの日々
Those bewildering days when the bond began,
気が付けば 近付く心の距離
before we knew it, the distance between our hearts shortened.
うまく紡げない 言葉だけど 不器用なりに
The words don't come out right, but in my own clumsy way,
歩いてきた 軌跡 巡る 奇跡
the trajectory we've walked is a recurring miracle.
いつか 枯れる運命でも 咲き誇る 花でいたい
Even if it's fated to wither someday, I want to be a flower in full bloom.
いつか 褪せる想いでも まだ夢見たいから
Even if the feelings fade someday, I still want to dream.
そうでしょ？
Isn't that right?
明日の明日もきっと 一人じゃ辿り着けない
Even the day after tomorrow, I probably can't reach it alone.
涙の数の想いだけ 心に 溢れてる
Just as many feelings as the number of tears are overflowing in my heart.
それでも 最後はあのように いつか消えてしまうのなら
Even so, if in the end it disappears like that one day,
伝え足りない気持ち 君に届くように
so that the feelings I haven't conveyed enough can reach you,
そっと今 願う
I gently pray now.
振り返れば今世 あの日見た可能性
Looking back on this life, the possibility I saw that day,
過去は未来への標 ふいに重なって解けて
the past is a signpost to the future, suddenly overlapping and unraveling.
ずっと うまく伝わらない でもいつだって感じてたよ
It hasn't always come across well, but I've always felt it.
きっと 出会いの意味は僕らが 決めるもの
Surely, the meaning of our meeting is something we decide.
そうでしょ？
Isn't that right?
明日の明日もきっと 大袈裟な未来じゃなくても
Even the day after tomorrow, even if it's not a grand future,
涙の数の絆で これから 幸せで
with bonds as many as the number of tears, may there be happiness from now on.
それでも 泣いたり笑ったり 傷付くこともあるでしょう
Even so, there will be times when we cry, laugh, or get hurt.
これまであった奇跡 いつも思い出して
Always remember the miracles we've had until now.
触れ合うたび 近付く奇跡
With every touch, a miracle draws closer
巡り会えた君との奇跡
A miracle that I met you
全てはここから
Everything starts...
始まる
...from here
心の弱さを見せること
Showing your heart's weakness...
存外 悪いことじゃない
...isn't necessarily a bad thing
6年分の笑顔を
Thank you for...
ありがとう
...six years' worth of smiles
これまで積み重ねた軌跡
The trajectory we've built up until now
思い出の集大成 現時点
The culmination of memories at this point
揺るぎないもの一つ
One unwavering thing...
言葉じゃ伝えられない
...that words cannot convey
それでもサヨナラはキズナの
Even so, "goodbye" is...
いつか辿り着く終着点
...the destination the bonds will one day reach
昇る日が沈むように
Just as the rising sun sets
夜に染まるように
Just as it becomes dyed in the night
だから永久を願う
That's why I pray for eternity
皆さんどうも、こんあくあー！
Hello everyone, kon-aqua!
ホロライブ所属、湊あくあです。
From Hololive, this is Minato Aqua.
ということで、マイクが変わってる！
And with that, the mic has changed!
ここからは生パフォーマンスでお送りしまーす！
From here on, I'll be bringing you a live performance!
ドキュメンタリー、YAGOOと対談してみたりとか、
The documentary, trying out a talk with YAGOO,
すごい声の可愛いナレーションがあったりとか、
having that really cute-voiced narration,
みんなと歌を歌ったりとか、
singing songs with everyone...
いろいろあったんですけれども、どうでしたか？
there's been a lot, but how was it?
今日は卒業ライブということで、
Since today is my graduation live,
私の最後のライブ！
this is my final live!
最後まで見てってね、お願いしまーす！
Please watch until the very end!
ハッシュタグ #湊あくあ卒業ライブ で、
Please tweet a lot using the hashtag
ぜひたくさんツイートしてください！
#MinatoAquaGraduationLIVE!
なんか日本トレンド1位、世界トレンド1位って
It says "Japan trend #1, World trend #1"
書いてあるわ、台本に。
here in the script.
台本とか言わないの！
Don't say "script"!
はい、ということでね、たくさんありがとうございます！
Yes, so, thank you all very much!
ということでね、湊あくあは今日で伝説になる！
And so, Minato Aqua becomes a legend today!
銀河一、伝説のアイドル、湊あくあを
Burn the image of the galaxy's number one,
目にしっかり焼き付けてね！
legendary idol Minato Aqua into your eyes!
絶対だよ！
Promise me!
次の曲へ行く前に、ちょっとね、あの、喉パッサパサ、
Before the next song, my throat is really dry...
緊張でパッサパサなんで、ちょっとお水を飲みます。
dry from nervousness, so I'm drinking some water.
ちょっと待って。
Wait a bit.
やばい、緊張すごいんだけど。
Man, I'm so nervous.
お水ってこんなに美味しいんだね。よし。
Water is so delicious. Alright.
お待たせしましたー！
Sorry to keep you waiting!
ハンドマイクかな？ヘッドセットに替えました。
It was a handheld mic, right? I changed to a headset.
可愛いでしょ。
It's cute, isn't it?
それでは、次の曲、聴いてください。
And now, please listen to the next song.
あくたんのこと好きすぎ☆ソング！
The "I Love Akutan Too Much" Song!
私、湊あくあ。
I'm Minato Aqua.
職業、スーパーウルトラ何でもパーフェクトなメイドさん！
Profession: Super Ultra Everything Perfect Maid!
今日もご主人様のために精一杯頑張っちゃうぞ！
Today too, I'll do my absolute best for Master!
ラブラブ、ラブラブ、メイドさんだぞ、イェーイ！
Lovey-dovey, lovey-dovey, I'm a maid! Yay!
あくたんのこと好きすぎ☆ソング
The "I Love Akutan Too Much" Song
よくできました！
Well done!
ドジっ子メイドは絶体絶命
The clumsy maid is in a desperate situation
お掃除洗濯 ほら汗だくだ
Cleaning, laundry, look, I'm covered in sweat
お料理焦げたらテヘペロ
If the food burns, "tehepero"!
許してご主人
Forgive me, Master
ゲームばかりして怒ってる
You're mad because I'm just playing games
プリティー猫フェイスでごまかすにゃ
I'll trick you with my pretty cat face, nya
お昼寝はメイドの性
Napping is a maid's nature
ご機嫌な夢見てスヤヤ
Dreaming happy dreams, fast asleep
エプロン カチューシャはハンドメイド
The apron and headband are handmade
トイレはいかないよ アイドルメイド
I don't go to the bathroom, I'm an idol maid
あー ご主人 ニヤついてる
Ah, Master, you're grinning
だめっ だめっ
No, no!
メイド服脱いだら ただの女の子だけど
Once I take off the maid uniform, I'm just an ordinary girl, but...
ご主人との思い出 作れますか？
Can we make memories together, Master?
ずっと仲良くしてね
Let's always get along well
はるか未来で しわくちゃになったって
Even in the far future, when we're all wrinkled up
思い出してくれるよね この
You'll remember this, right?
チュー オムライス
Chu! Omelet rice!
あくたんのこと 1212
About Akutan, 1, 2, 1, 2!
みんなであくあオリ曲メドレーいくよ！
Everyone, let's go with the Aqua original song medley!
きらきらと輝こうか
Shall we sparkle and shine?
間違えちゃっても大丈夫
It's okay if we make mistakes
できないことできるようになる
We'll become able to do what we couldn't
なれるよ 仲間がいるから
We can do it because we have friends
疲れちゃったら止まろうか
Shall we stop if we get tired?
少し眠ったら また歩み
After a little sleep, we'll walk again
したいことしたいようにしなくちゃ
I have to do what I want to do, the way I want
私じゃないでしょ
Or else it wouldn't be me, right?
忘れないよ この思いは
I won't forget these feelings
重ねて もっと届くように
Let them pile up so they reach further
変えられるんだ 変えていくんだ
Things can be changed, and I will change them
きらきらしたいから
Because I want to sparkle
画面越しご挨拶
Greetings through the screen
好きだって言っちゃって 全然可愛くない
Saying I like you isn't cute at all
勝手に凹んだって 泣いてみたって 全然可愛くない
Getting depressed or crying on my own isn't cute at all
君だって同じ ダメ降りの自称です
You're the same, a hopeless self-proclaimed [fan?]
そんな優しくして あたしに気があるの？
Being so kind... are you into me?
どんな時間 どんな予感 カピハピニング
No matter the time or premonition, copy-happening
中毒症状 依存度MAX メンタル崩壊
Addiction symptoms, dependence MAX, mental collapse
あなたのことを もっともっと知りたい
I want to know more and more about you
ヨーコソ！ Sweet Carnival!
Welcome! Sweet Carnival!
あなたの「大好き」がいっぱい
Full of your "favorites"
溢れた街
A town overflowing
鳴らそう 胸のファンファーレ
Let's sound the fanfare in our hearts
色彩はもっと奇跡が
The colors will bring out more miracles
飛び出してくる ここは ホロライブ！
Springing forth, this is Hololive!
私エイムに愛されしガールなんてね
I'm a girl loved by my aim, just kidding
誇らないけどさ
Not that I'm boasting or anything
なんてったってできる気がするわ
I feel like I can do anything after all
ゲームの世界ならならば
If it's in the world of games
私エイムに愛されしガールなんてね
I'm a girl loved by my aim, just kidding
誇らないままさ
I'll just keep not boasting
狙いを定めりゃ バンバンバン
If I set my sights, bang bang bang!
それなら準備はオッケー 踏み込もうぜ
Then the preparation is okay, let's step in
会いたさが優勝です
The desire to see you wins
おすまし顔のフィアラをちょっと見せつけて
Showing off a little of my prim and proper face
甘々じゃまだ足りない
Being all lovey-dovey isn't enough yet
本音がバレて全て泡になっていく
My true feelings are exposed and everything turns to foam
ねえ キャリー お姫様のアナタが
Hey, carry me, the princess you...
いつかありふれた幸せで
Someday, with common happiness...
満たされたらいいのにな
I wish I could be filled up
合言葉はよそ見しない
The password is "don't look away"
覚悟ができたならオッケー
If you're prepared, then okay
ワンツースリー ここからは
One, two, three, from here on
呼び捨てでもいいけど
You can call me without an honorific, but...
これくらいのわがままは
This much selfishness is...
女の子してるってことじゃん
...just me being a girl, isn't it?
ワンバイワン 言葉で教えてほしい
One by one, I want you to tell me in words
ラブゲームみたい
Like a love game
最初は泣いてばかりだったっけ
At first, was I always just crying?
もう大丈夫
It's okay now.
いつもありがとうね
Thank you for everything.
もう大丈夫
It's okay now.
君が隣にいてくれる
Because you're by my side.
もう大丈夫
It's okay now.
君が愛してくれる
Because you love me.
君が名前を呼んでくれる
Because you call my name.
君のサンタは？
Who is your Santa?
君のチニクは？
Who is your flesh and blood?
君の女神は？
Who is your goddess?
今日の主役は？
Who is today's star?
才能ない努力は無駄
Effort without talent is a waste,
やめろとか
just quit, they say.
そうかもって
There are times when
飲まれそうな時もある
I'm about to believe that.
大嫌い大嫌い
I hated, hated
弱虫だった
my cowardly self.
もっと強くなるために
To become even stronger,
君の最推しにしてよ
please make me your number one!
ハートをくれた分だけ
For every heart you give me,
私は君に恋する
I'll fall in love with you.
ハートをくれた分だけ
For every heart you give me,
私は夢を叶えるね
I'll make my dreams come true.
愛して愛して
Love me, love me.
一緒に行こう　頂上目指す
Let's go together, aiming for the top.
私を見てよ
Look at me.
お別れよろしい
Are you ready to say goodbye?
そうやって描いた今日を通り越して
Passing through the today I painted like that,
明日はもっと君の側へ前へ　前へ
Tomorrow, I'll be even closer to you, moving forward, forward.
少しずつ進んでいく　一歩十歩百歩踏み出して
Advancing little by little, taking one step, ten steps, a hundred steps.
揺らめいてる君が青くにじむ　青くにじむ綺麗に
The wavering you blurs into blue, beautifully blurring into blue.
会いに行く　会いに行く今すぐ
I'm coming to see you, coming to see you right now.
ミティア　君に届けて
Meteor, let it reach you.
凍える夜は暖かな愛を
For the freezing nights, a warm love.
嫌われる前に嫌ってきたくせに
Even though I used to hate before being hated,
正しく居たいと思うの
I want to stay true.
ユニバース　綻びがいつか
Uni-birth, one day the tear will...
花開くように春を待ってる
wait for spring like a flower blooming.
憧れた姿と違ってるはずが
Even though it was supposed to be different from the figure I longed for,
正しく居たいと思うの
I want to stay true.
ユニバース　生まれ変わっても
Uni-birth, even if I'm reborn,
私がいいと思わせたいよ　だってさ
I want to make you think it has to be me, because...
駆け抜ける今が未来の私
The now I race through is the future me.
待った無しの1回きりを生きてる
Living a one-time life with no waiting.
勝ちも価値もないらしく見えるじゃないか
Doesn't it look like there's no victory or value?
この後悔を笑わないで
Don't laugh at this regret.
負けたくない悔し涙が
Even on days when tears of frustration
溢れ出した日でさえも
from not wanting to lose overflowed,
無駄じゃない私らしさを
they're not in vain, because
作ってくから
they build my identity.
大丈夫大丈夫心配ないよ
It's okay, it's okay, don't worry.
大丈夫大丈夫
It's okay, it's okay.
全力で走り続けたんだ
I kept running at full power.
君ならできるさ
You can do it too.
喜びも悲しみも
There are people to share
分かち合える人がいる
both joy and sadness with.
初めて気づいたんだ
I realized for the first time
一人じゃないんだって
that I'm not alone.
A-Q-U-A
仲間たちと叶えたい
I want to make it come true with my friends.
夢はきっとこの場所で
Dreams will surely be in this place.
あくあ色に輝く
Shining in Aqua's color.
A-Q-U-A　行くよ
A-Q-U-A, here we go!
レッツゴー・ファイト・ウィン！
Let's go, fight, win!
A-Q-U-A
イエス・あくあ・フォー・ザ・ウィン！
Yes, Aqua, for the win!
海想列車も怖くはない
I'm not afraid of the marine memory train,
夢中で
absorbed...
駆け抜けた日々は夢じゃないから
Because the days I raced through weren't a dream.
正解なんて相変わらずまだ　分からないけど
I still don't know the right answer, as usual, but...
目の前に広がるこの景色を見ていたい
I want to keep looking at this scenery spreading before my eyes.
ああ　君と一緒にこの景色を見ていたい
Ah, I want to keep looking at this scenery together with you.
いていたい
I want to be here
あぁ...やりきった。長かった！
Phew... I did it. It was long!
ちょっと喉パサパサなので水を飲みます。
My throat is a bit dry, so I'm going to drink some water.
やばい...やばいパサパサだな...
Oh boy... it's really dry...
お水が美味しすぎる。ちょっと待って。
The water is so delicious. Wait a bit.
とんでもないわ。あぁ、ちょっと疲れた。
Unbelievable. Ah, I'm a bit tired.
あれ？なんだこれ？
Huh? What's this?
新しいマイク。
A new microphone.
ということで、ありがとうございました！
オリ曲メドレーでした。
So, thank you very much!
That was the original song medley.
私の歌とダンスいかがだってございましょうか？
How were my singing and dancing?
やばい、オリジナルハンドマイクになりました。
どうも！
Wow, I've got an original hand-held microphone.
Hello!
ちょっとめっちゃさ、ちょっと息やばくて。
I'm... really out of breath.
とんでもないことになってる。あ、コメントね、
It's gotten crazy. Oh, the comments...
すごいいな、やすぎてあのね読めません。はい。
They're amazing, they're so fast I can't read them. Yes.
読めないです。もうとんでもない加速の量し
ありがとうございますみんな。
I can't read them. Thank you everyone
for the incredible speed.
あぁ疲れた、ちょっと待って。
Ah I'm tired, wait a moment.
あぁ気を取り直して。ずっとまだ緊張も
冷めぬやらぬところではありますが。
Ah, let me compose myself. I'm still feeling nervous,
but...
え、ま最後だからね。え、全部オリ曲歌いたいな
って思ってたので。
Well, since it's the last one.
I wanted to sing all my original songs.
全部歌うにはもう24時間必要だということで、
激長のメドレーにさせていただきます。ありがとうございます。
Since it would take 24 hours to sing them all, I made
it an extra-long medley. Thank you very much.
6年間ね、こんなにたくさんオリジナル曲を
作ったんだなと。
In these six years, I've really made so many
original songs.
本当にたくさんの歌を歌えて幸せでした。
ありがとうございます。
I was really happy to be able to sing so many
songs. Thank you very much.
携わってくださった皆さん、聞いてくれたみんな。
本当にどうもありがとう。
Everyone involved, everyone who listened.
Thank you so much.
え、次の曲はですね、このライブの直前に
動画が上がった曲です。
Um, the next song is one that was released
as a video right before this live.
あぁちょっと緊張してきた。あぁ。
ちょっと水飲も。ちょっと待って。
Ah, I'm getting a bit nervous. Ah.
Let me drink some water. Wait a bit.
やばいちょっと待って。水飲みすぎ？
Oh boy, wait a bit. Am I drinking too much water?
あのね、人は緊張するとね、喉が渇くから
水を飲みたくなるらしいですよ。
You know, they say when people get nervous,
their throat gets dry so they want to drink water.
噂によると。ということで。
According to rumors. So with that said.
よし。(深呼吸) え、みんなへ。
Alright. (Deep breath) Um, to everyone.
6年間の感謝を込めて歌います。
I will sing with gratitude for these six years.
次の曲聞いてください。今日初めて歌います。
Please listen to the next song.
I'll be singing it for the first time today.
きみいろプリンセス。
Kimi-iro Princess.
#きみいろプリンセス
作詞 Junky / 湊あくあ 作曲・編曲 Junky
#Kimi-iro Princess
Lyrics: Junky / Minato Aqua Composition/Arrangement: Junky
いつかの憧れた 華やかな世界
The glamorous world I once yearned for
強がってみせても 「怖いよ 怖いよ」
Even if I act tough, "I'm scared, I'm scared"
メリーゴーランドの中で ひとりぼっちみたい
Like being all alone on a merry-go-round
掠れそうな声で 【気付いて 気付いて】
With a voice that's about to fade away
[Notice me, notice me]
群衆の中で キミの声が聞こえる
In the middle of the crowd, I can hear your voice
聞き違いじゃない 【呼んでよ 呼んでよ】
It's not a mistake [Call my name, call my name]
聞こえたその声に 心が熱くなる
At the sound of that voice, my heart grows warm
ダメダメでもいいかな 隣にいたいよ
Is it okay even if I'm no good?
I want to be by your side
だってだってだってだってだってキミだから
Because, because, because, because, because it's you
だからきっと たぶん絶対
So surely, probably, definitely
これはキミのせい 覚えておいて
This is your fault, please remember that
秘密にしてるの
I'm keeping it a secret
キミの「大好き」の証 教えてよ
Tell me the proof of your "love"
魔法みたいに輝いて 【聞かせてよ】
Shine like magic and [let me hear it]
おとぎのようなお話 【見せてみて】
Try showing me a story like a fairy tale
私ひとりじゃ叶わない (Oh Oh Oh Oh)
I can't make it come true alone (Oh Oh Oh Oh)
キミが隣にただいるだけで
Just having you by my side,
プリンセスになれるの
I can become a princess.
運命で出会って　一緒に見た世界
Met by fate, the world we saw together.
改まって照れるけど　ありがとう大好きだよ
I'm shy to say it now, but thank you, I love you.
毎日の中で　キミの声が聞こえる
In every single day, I hear your voice.
世界中で１番　私が幸せだよ
I'm the happiest person in the whole world.
ティアラも　ドレスだって　ガラスの靴なんかも
The tiara, the dress, even the glass slippers,
全部いらないわ　キミが全て
I don't need any of them, you are everything.
キミと歩いたキセキ
The miracle of walking with you.
絶対だよって約束　覚えてる？
Do you remember the promise that it's absolute?
私ひとりじゃ　キミがいなくちゃ
By myself, without you here,
輝かないわ
I won't shine.
嘘みたいなほど　キミを大好きな私
So much it's like a lie, how much I love you.
(I LOVE YOU)
ぱれっとみたいに彩って
Like a palette, coloring it in.
(I LOVE YOU SO MUCH)
ホントだけの物語
A story of only truth.
(I LOVE YOU)
未来はどうなるのかな
I wonder what the future holds.
(Oh Oh Oh Oh)
暗闇もない　不安も消える
No darkness, anxiety disappears.
ずっと進んでいこう
Let's keep going forever.
これからも私を見てて
Please keep watching me from now on.
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
「きみいろプリンセス」でした！
That was "Kimiiro Princess"!
やばい緊張やばい、どうしよう、おかしくなっちゃいそう。あはは。
Man, I'm so nervous, what should I do? I feel like I'm going crazy. Haha.
え、ということでこの曲はね、
So, about this song,
「あくあ色ぱれっと」のアンサーソングとして、
as an answer song to "Aquairo Palette,"
Junkyさんと一緒に作りました。
I made it together with Junky-san.
私もちょっとだけ作詞をさせていただきました。
I also helped out a little with the lyrics.
いっぱい聴いてください。お願いします。
Please listen to it a lot. Thank you.
あー、やばい。え、もうここまで来ちゃったのか。やば。
Ah, man... Wait, have I already come this far? Man.
やば... ちょっと待って、水飲む。
Man... Wait a sec, I'll drink some water.
あー、ここまで来ちゃったの？
Ah... have I already come this far?
やばい、どうしよう。もうここまで歌っちゃったんだ。
Man, what should I do? I've already sung this much.
いやマジか。ちょっと何か、やっと実感が沸いてきた。やばい。
Seriously? It's finally starting to sink in. Man.
やばい... やばいしか言ってないな。
Man... I'm just saying "man" over and over.
よし。
Alright.
泣きそうなんだけど、あはは。
I'm about to cry, haha.
泣いちゃうこれ... 待って。
I'm gonna cry... wait.
え、本当にちょっとさ、あの、次の曲ボロボロでも許してくれますか？
Seriously, will you forgive me if the next song is a total mess?
ま、ちょっとお話をね、させていただきたいと思うんですけれども。
Well, I'd like to talk for a bit, if that's okay.
いいですか？ えーと、喋りますね。
Is that okay? Okay, I'll talk now.
えーと、泣いても笑ってもこれで卒業ということで。
Well, whether I cry or laugh, this is my graduation.
アイドルにとって「死」っていうのは、
For an idol, I believe that "death"
みんなに忘れられることだと私は思ってます。
is being forgotten by everyone.
これからも私は私でいるよ。
I'll still be myself from now on.
卒業してもまだまだ生きていくんだから。
Even after I graduate, I'll still be living.
だからみんなも私のこと忘れないでね。
So please, everyone, don't forget me.
忘れないで。本当に...
Don't forget me. Really...
あー...
Ah...
何かを始めるときって必ず
When you start something,
終わりも一緒に来るけど。
the end always comes with it.
...考えるタイプなんですけど
...I'm the type of person who thinks about things like that.
私はホロライブに入った時から、
Ever since I joined Hololive,
最後は輝いて終わりたいって思ってました。漠然とね
I've always thought I wanted to end things while shining. Vaguely, that is.
そう思うと、ある意味この卒業も、私の一つの夢だったんだなと思います
Thinking about it, in a way, this graduation was also one of my dreams.
物心ついた時からずっとアイドルになりたかった
Ever since I can remember, I've always wanted to be an idol.
私、保育園の時の夢がアイドルだったんですよ。恥ずい！
My dream back in kindergarten was to be an idol. How embarrassing!
本当は、ちょっとスカしてケーキ屋さんとかおもちゃ屋さんとか親に言ってたりはしたんですけど
Actually, I used to act a bit cool and tell my parents I wanted to be a pastry chef or a toy shop owner.
キラキラ輝くアイドルになりたいな、歌って踊れるアイドルになりたいな、みんなに愛されるアイドルになりたいなって思ってました。凄くない？
But I secretly thought, 'I want to be a sparkling idol, an idol who can sing and dance, an idol loved by everyone.' Isn't it amazing?
夢を叶えたんだよ、みんなのおかげで
I've made that dream come true, thanks to all of you.
自分の部屋と一台のパソコン。暗い部屋でただパソコンに向かって喋っていただけの私が
Me, who was just talking to a computer in a dark room with nothing but my PC.
私の環境が、みんなのおかげでどんどん、どんどん変わっていって
My environment has been changing more and more, thanks to everyone.
本当にこんなことってあるんだね
Something like this can really happen, can't it?
この奇跡が、積み重ねてきた思いが
This miracle, all these feelings I've built up...
きっと私のこれからを支えてくれると思う
...I'm sure they will support me from now on.
そういう風に今思えてることを誇りに思います
I'm proud that I'm able to feel this way right now.
だから改めて、みんな本当にありがとう！
So, once again, thank you all so much!
これさ、なんかさ、お辞儀した秒数だけみたいなのあったりするかな？もっといっぱいお辞儀しといたほうがいいかな？
I wonder if there's something like... a record for how long I bowed? Maybe I should've bowed even more?
本当にみんなありがとう
Thank you all so much, truly.
それでは...
And now...
ちょっと名残惜しいんですけども
It's a little sad to say goodbye, but...
私は今日、伝説になりますから
...because today, I'm going to become a legend.
よし！歌えるかな？
All right! Can I sing this?
次は最後の曲です
The next song will be the last.
それでは、最後の曲、聞いてください
And now, please listen to the final song.
あくあ色ぱれっと！
Aqua Iro Palette!
何をしても不器用で
No matter what I do, I'm clumsy
何かとミスしてばっか
And I'm always making mistakes
ダメダメな私だって
Even for a hopeless me like that
できる事があるの
There are things I can do
へこんで悲しくたって
Even when I'm down and sad
笑顔にしてあげるんだ
I'll make you smile
ここにいるから早く
I'm right here, so hurry
私を見つけてね
And find me
#あくあ色ぱれっと
#Aqua Iro Palette
I love you!
これで本当の本当にラストです！最後まで全力で盛り上がります！
This is really, truly the last one! Let's get fired up until the very end!
いつでも隣にいるし、
I'm always by your side,
いつでも一緒に笑える
And we can always laugh together
私をたくさん知って
Know more about me
たくさん好きって言って
And tell me you love me a lot
ワガママで朝も苦手
I'm selfish and not a morning person
ドジだしダメダメだけど
I'm clumsy and hopeless, but
それでも私の事を見ててね
Even so, please keep watching me
描く夢の未来へ
To the future of the dream I draw
描く夢の未来へ続く
Continuing on the path to the future I envision
道をキミと歩けますように
I hope I can walk it with you
ねえもっと 好きになって もらいたいの
Hey, I want you to like me even more
頭の中は君ばっかってゆーか
My head is full of nothing but you
そっぽなんて向いてないで
Don't look away from me
あーもう ヤキモキしちゃうわ あーあ
Oh, geez, you're making me so anxious, ah-ah
ずっとずっと 好きがいいの
I want us to like each other forever
心の奥までトキメイちゃうくらいに
So much that my heart throbs to its core
こっち向いててよね ダーリン？
Keep looking this way, okay, darling?
あーもう 離さないから 絶対に 絶対ね
Oh, geez, I'll never let you go, never ever
あはは、もうボロボロだよ...
Ahaha, I'm already a mess...
みんなありがとう...
Thank you everyone...
あ、やばい、ひどい顔してない？ 大丈夫？
Oh no, do I look terrible? Am I okay?
キミがいるから私
Because you're here,
いつでも頑張れるんだ
I can always do my best
落ち込んで悲しくたって
Even when I'm feeling down and sad
キミがいるから...
Because you're here...
今日が本当に最高の日になりました！
Today has become a truly wonderful day!
この景色を見せてくれて、本当に本当にありがとう！
Thank you so, so much for showing me this view!
世界中、あくあ色に染まれー！
Whole world, be dyed in Aqua's color!
キミがいるから歩いてこれた
I was able to keep walking because you were here
キミがいなくちゃ前も見れない
I can't even look ahead without you
嫌なこととか辛いこととかあったって
Even if there were bad things or painful things
キミの力でここまで笑ってこれたんだ
I was able to smile until now because of your strength
今度はもっと私がグッと引っ張って
This time, I'll pull you along much harder
連れて行くんだ
And take you with me
キミがいるから私がいるの
I exist because you are here
そんな私を愛してくれる？
Will you love me as I am?
ねえもっと ねえもっと
Hey, more, hey, more
まだもっと 受け止めてよね！
Still more, please accept me!
ねえいい？
Is that okay?
さあ声を上げて！
Now, raise your voices!
ねえもっと ねえもっと
Hey, more, hey, more
好きになってもらいたいの
I want you to like me even more
わたしばかりみたいに
Like you're only looking at me
そっぽなんて向かせないわ
I won't let you look away
ねえほら 夢中にしちゃうわ あーあ
Hey, look, I'll make you crazy for me, ah-ah
ずっとずっと 好きがいいの
I want us to like each other forever
心も体も染まっちゃうくらいに
So much that our hearts and bodies are dyed
こっち向いててよね ダーリン？
Keep looking this way, okay, darling?
あーもう 離さないから 絶対に
Oh, geez, I'll never let you go, never
絶対ね 絶対よ
Never ever, for sure
約束だよ！
It's a promise!
love you, love you...
ここまで応援してくれたファンのみんな、
To all the fans who have supported me this far,
仲良くしてくれたホロメン、
To the Hololive members who were so kind to me,
支えてくれたスタッフの皆さん、本当にありがとう！
To all the staff who supported me, thank you so much!
ホロライブ最高！
Hololive is the best!
愛しちゃう、もっと。
I'll love you more.
ありがとう！
Thank you!
湊あくあ ⚓ 卒業ライブ
あくあ色に染まれ！
Minato Aqua Graduation LIVE
Minato Aqua ⚓ Graduation LIVE
Be dyed in Aqua's color!
Minato Aqua Graduation LIVE